<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Remarks upon a tract, intituled A treatise of humane reason, and upon Mr. Warren's late defence of it. / By Sir George Blundell.</title>
            <author>Blundell, George, Sir.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B01684</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3361A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R172804</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">51617757</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 51617757</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175149</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B01684)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175149)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2716:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Remarks upon a tract, intituled A treatise of humane reason, and upon Mr. Warren's late defence of it. / By Sir George Blundell.</title>
                  <author>Blundell, George, Sir.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>112 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jacob Tonson, at the Judges Head in Chancery-Lane, near Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Clifford, M. --  (Martin), d. 1677. --  Treatise of humane reason.</term>
               <term>Faith and reason --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:175149:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175149:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>REMARKS</hi> UPON A TRACT, INTITULED, A TREATISE OF <hi>HUMANE REASON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND Upon M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Warren</hi>'s late Defence of it.</p>
            <p>By Sir <hi>George Blundell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Jacob Tonſon,</hi> at the <hi>Judges Head</hi> in <hi>Chancery-Lane,</hi> near <hi>Fleetſtreet:</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:175149:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175149:2"/>
            <head>AN <hi>ADVERTISEMENT</hi> TO THE READER. </head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Had no Intentions until lately to expoſe theſe <hi>REMARKS,</hi> (which were made in the year <hi>76,</hi> for my privat Diverſion) to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Cenſure of an Age ſo much diſtracted <hi>in Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:175149:3"/>but finding that the Approbation of this <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> (after ſome men's endeavours to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute it) doth ſtill remain in the minds of many, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whoſe Inclinations to Novelty (it may be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped) that the Variety, as well as force of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, may prevail to make a new <hi>Anſwer</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable: and ſeeing like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Enemies of the poor <hi>Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:175149:3"/>encreaſe ſo much both in numbers and audacity, as to attack it on every ſide, by moſt graceleſs and inhumane attempts: I thought it the Duty of an <hi>Orthodox</hi> (tho' an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy) <hi>Profeſſor,</hi> to put my <hi>Mite</hi> into the <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban</hi> to help to ſupport it.</p>
            <p>But if it ſhall be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther objected, that I have not well timed the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of theſe <hi>Remarks,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:175149:4"/>in regard the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Treatiſe</hi> may poſſibly be dead; to this I ſhall only anſwer, That no <hi>Books</hi> in any Age have been priviledged from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Confuted or Suppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed (after the death of their <hi>Authors</hi>) if their <hi>Contents</hi> were offenſive to our <hi>Laws</hi> or <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:175149:4"/>
            <head>REMARKS UPON A TREATISE OF <hi>HUMANE REASON.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">To the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Treatiſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN reading your Treatiſe (I deal franckly with you) I was much diſappointed, for I did expect a diſcourſe of the Origen, Nature, and Conveyance of Humane Reaſon to all the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:175149:5"/>of Men, and in order to this that you would have treated.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Of its primitive Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Deſcent from God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to Man at his Creation.</p>
            <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> Of its Perſpicacity and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in the ſtate of Innocency.</p>
            <p n="3">3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> Of its impaired Condition in <hi>Adam</hi> himſelf and the firſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, before many of thoſe vices, which ſo much weaken it now, were practiſed in the world.</p>
            <p n="4">4<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, That you would by ſome new Ratiocinations have either confirmed that Opinion of the Conveyance of <hi>Humane Reaſon</hi> to all <hi>Adam</hi>'s Poſterity, which is generally agreed on to be the beſt account; or that you would have diſcovered ſome other more ſatisfactory to the Readers: Since the moſt prevalent Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is, That the Rational Soul
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:175149:5"/>doth not inherit this Degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, etraduce or by deſcent; but that it is a Spirit infuſed, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with greater purity and intelligence than can poſſibly be exerted in the humane <hi>Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> as it is now ſtated, from which ſome <hi>Scepticks</hi> take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to Cavil.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, That (for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and amendment of men, and the vindication of our beſt Faculty) you would have made ſome acute and new <hi>Eſſay</hi> (at leaſt) to remind us, that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Humane Reaſon is ſo much obſtructed and dulled by meer ſloth in ſome, and injured and depraved by paſſions and Vices in others, that it ſeems to be fallen from the Glory and Splendor of the great <hi>Luminary</hi> in the Heavens, to the ſmall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of a <hi>Star</hi> in the Sky:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175149:6"/>For ſuch was the proportion which Rationality bore in the uncorrupted Nature of Man, to that which is ſo much decayed and weakned not only by <hi>Adam</hi>'s Fall, but alſo by the faults and ill management of his degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Poſterity ever ſince.</p>
            <p>But in lieu of all this, I find a peremptory Claim made, and Pretenſions to aſſert Humane Reaſon's Title not only to an Office of Inquiſition, but alſo to a Power Judicial in Divine Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; for in ſearching out, it muſt likewiſe determine in its own Court (as you ſtyle it) which is the right Religion, and upon this account, that the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Chriſtian who is, or ought to be its Friend and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject upon the beſt and trueſt foundation, doth above all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers deny it its due ſtation and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:175149:6"/>dominion; but how valid this Title is, and the conſequent Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, muſt be diſcovered by examining the enſuing Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</p>
            <p>In the firſt <hi>Page,</hi> whereof you declare your inducement to make an inquiry into the nature and quality of your Religion, to be the duty of your private Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that your intereſt in humane ſociety was the Cauſe of your offering to the view of others the effects of that ſearch; which if beneficial to your ſelf and others (as upon the ſcore of Charity we may ſuppoſe you believe by your publiſhing it) is thanks and praiſe-worthy; but if otherwiſe, then upon a ſight and acknowledgment of your miſtake, a true Repentance, and all poſſible endeavours to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the ſpreading of your Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175149:7"/>is only pardonable.</p>
            <p>In the 2d. and 3d. <hi>Pages</hi> you have laid the foundation of all your opinion contained in the following Treatiſe; if therefore upon examination this ſhall be found faulty, your ſmall Fabrick will with much more eaſe be totally demoliſhed.</p>
            <p>Here you acknowledge the Hiſtory of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Fall as it is ſtated in the Scriptures, and the miſerable Conſequence of it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him and his lapſed Poſterity, as to the great vitiating and blur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the eye-ſight of our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, that (to uſe your own expreſſion) <hi>One had great need of a better eye-ſight than is left us by the fall of our firſt Fore-father,</hi> to guide us amongſt many errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, to the right way of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I queſtion not but this will be allowed you as Orthodox;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:175149:7"/>and if inſtead of your ſo anxious Debate and Conſideration (in the next place) you had apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your ſelf to receive the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and obey the Precepts contained in the reſt of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture (according to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Catholick Church) they would have convinced you, that Tradition, Revelation, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, and the Grace of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, which teacheth the right uſe of the reſt, are prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Divine Providence, as the beſt Pilots to ſteer your Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in this dubious Voyage, and would certainly have preſerved you from ſo ſudden a revolt from the Truth, and ſo direct a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to your own Notion (within four lines after) by pitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon your own Reaſon for that clear-ſighted Guide, which it ſelf ſo much wanted before:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:175149:8"/>This is that irreparable flaw in your Foundation, which cauſes the ruine of your whole Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructure.</p>
            <p>You have penned the next Clauſe darkly for a blind (I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) to the contradiction in the former, <hi>If Reaſon takes ſuch dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions as it ought and may do before it ſets forth:</hi> If you mean thoſe Directions which I mentioned before (as indeed it may and ought) then the ſubject of the Queſtion is altogether loſt, for ſo Reaſon alone cannot be ſtated as the beſt Guide; but if you mean ſuch Directions as Natural Reaſon ſhall give it ſelf, then the ſame thing will both guide and be guided to the ſame end; Now a Guide ſubject to ſuch Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruities as theſe cannot but bring you into Errors, but not through them to happineſs at laſt, which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:175149:8"/>in this Clauſe alſo you as incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruouſly, as vainly aſſert.</p>
            <p>In the next place you digreſs, by bidding defiance to thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Enemies which you expect ſhould attack your Doctrine (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving as you boaſt) Coup't up their Front and Reer in the <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſcade</hi> of this <hi>Dilemma; That thoſe who diſpute moſt againſt the Power and Priviledges of Humane Reaſon, do it becauſe their own rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon perſwades them to that belief, and ſo whether the Victory be on mine or on their ſide, are equally defeated.</hi> Yeur Argument is pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel to this: He that is ſick and from a true ſence of his Diſeaſe acknowledgeth his weakneſs by that very acknowledment makes it manifeſt that he is well, and he that is in the like Condition, but is ſo inſenſible of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, that he conceits he is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175149:9"/>in health, is well alſo; whereas the indiſpoſition of both remains, but the laſt labours under the moſt deſperate Symptoms, (your own Caſe) ſee now your Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory or rather your plain De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat either way.</p>
            <p>Neither (in my weak opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) is your Anſwer to the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation which you quote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Wits more convincing than your Victory was trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant: for if lapſed Reaſon in its moſt accurate ſtate (as it is poſſeſſed by the Wits) may be made a ſlave to the wills, inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, or the prejudices of men, or be apt to be wanting in any part of its neceſſary duty for ſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardous a paſſage, (all which you acknowledge in your <hi>fourth page</hi>) then it cannot appear to judicious and conſidering men to be a Guide ſolely to be relyed on in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:175149:9"/>this grand Affair; nor can even the weakeſt Underſtandings be ſo abſolutely unbyaſſed, as to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Errors unblameable, as you have ſtated this Caſe, for every <hi>Scioliſt</hi> knows that your advancing the humane Faculty into an Office too high, for it is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which intails a juſt condemnation upon all ſuch Errors as are conſequential to that.</p>
            <p>But if ſuch fatal miſtakes be the meed of the Wits, what Confuſion ſhall we have when all ſorts of people whether men, women, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (for you exempt none) ſhall be allowed the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge to govern themſelves from within, without the leaſt regard had either to Example or Authority, or any thing elſe whatſoever, eſpecially ſince de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable Experience manifeſts
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:175149:10"/>that neither the Penalties of hu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mane nor of divine Laws, nor the immediate Judgments of Gods own hand, can reſtrain ſome even of all degrees of men from perpetrating the greateſt crimes, and falling into the moſt barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Practices as well as Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? is it not plain before you in this Caſe, that more of God's glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and regiment will be found among the Fowls of the Air, and Beaſts of the Deſart, than among thoſe who ſhall practiſe your a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable doctrine? For even among ſuch Animals, ſome foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps appear both of Authority and Example; nor can they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit either blaſphemy or idolatry, the two inevitable, as well as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controllable products of your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable opinions, while you phantaſtically pretend to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, I know not what univerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:175149:10"/>and perpetuity of Error, by broaching <hi>Myriads</hi> every day, ſo long as the minds of the Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſhall continue injudicious and wavering.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>5th page</hi> you ſeem to be ſenſible that you have too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſterially and raſhly aſſerted Humane Reaſon's abſolute abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to judge of Spiritual Truths, by acknowledging, <hi>that the</hi> what <hi>and the</hi> how <hi>of religious Myſteries are out of its ſight, and that it muſt make uſe of thoſe helps which God hath prepared for us to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to make them viſible as ſuch.</hi> This is the true ſenſe of your Clauſe, to which all Catholicks will agree, for it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied but if the Myſteries of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion are delivered down to us upon a ſupernatural account, but that our natural Capacity and Reaſon will need proportionable
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:175149:11"/>helps to enable it to apprehend them; how plain is it therefore that (from a high Conceit of your parts) you deſigned to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe phantaſtical Phraſes for new Notions upon weak under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings.</p>
            <p>For a Cloſe to this Paragraph, you are reduced to trifle with one of <hi>Democritus</hi> his Allegories, as if we ſhall find truth in our hearts, as we ſee Heaven in a Well; and this, you aſſert, is very applicable to your matter. If ſo, then accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your Metaphorical Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, your Diſciples muſt not only leave ſearching the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures for the true Religion, and paying their Adoration to the Deity, for Eternal Happineſs; but, on the contrary, they muſt look down into natural Reaſon, to find out the firſt, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, worſhip themſelves to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:175149:11"/>obtain the ſecond. Theſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, indeed, are entirely new, and ſuitable to the wretched Conceits of the forlorn Votaries in the Covent of <hi>Bethlehem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſixth Page you have quoted ſo tragical an Objection (as you call it) that, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding your endeavours in 8 ſubſequent pages to give it an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer (in my mean opinion) you come very much ſhort of it, <hi>viz. To allow this liberty, would beget as many Religions as there are ſeveral perſons, and conſequently draw af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it ſuch diſorder and confuſion, as is inconſiſtent, not only with the Quiet, but the very Being of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Society.</hi> Now, the truth of this Objection is ſo evident to all who have either ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered the unſteady and vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous condition of lapſed Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or have read the paſt, or do
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:175149:12"/>(at all) obſerve the preſent ſtate of affairs in the World, that they need not expect any other Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to evince, that difference of Opinions (eſpecially in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion) hath ever had ill effects in dividing of Affections, although not to the ſame degree in all Ages and Places: but yet, according to the circumſtances of times and opportunities, the temper of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſons, as well as that of publick Government, the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities which did ariſe from thence proved more or leſs miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous to Humane Society.</p>
            <p>Neither did thoſe differing Sects of Philoſophers (you quote) ſo peaceably agree (if you will truſt Hiſtory) as not to envy, ſcandalize, nay murther one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which (poſſibly) might have occaſioned publick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, had they not been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:175149:12"/>by the juncture of Affairs in thoſe times, and prudence of Governors, which preſerves <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> and <hi>Amſterdam</hi> in Peace at this day, notwithſtanding the aptneſs of thoſe Cities (as well as all others infeſted with Sects) to break out into Tumults, not to quote late inſtances.</p>
            <p>But however this inſtance (as it is ſtated by your ſelf) of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Opinions dividing Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, and the Philoſophers their Diſciples; doth not amount to ſo wild and independent Frenzy, as to give every ſingle perſon (how mean ſoever in degree, or incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent for parts) leave to become an uncontrollable Pope in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or conſtitute himſelf an indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual Church; and (in effect) to practice what Morals he liſts, (ſo much the Conſequences of Faith) by governi g himſelf
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:175149:13"/>from within, not having any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard either to Example or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority (the grand ligaments of Order) or any thing elſe; which Poſition not only defaces the Forms and Superſtructures of all Government both Eccleſiaſtical and Civil, but raſes out all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains and foundations of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Society; therefore no Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory can make mention of ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious a practice in the world, what ever (<hi>page</hi> the <hi>9th</hi>) you wrongfully affirm of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens.</p>
            <p>And now it would be but tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling and delaying the Reader to quote the particular and ſo well known Inſtances both in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and ſacred Story, that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in Religion, nay ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Sects under the ſame general profeſſion as well in the Wars betwixt the <hi>Gentiles</hi> and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:175149:13"/>the <hi>Jews</hi> as either party among themſelves, have cauſed the moſt inveterate Feuds and Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacres, and the greateſt deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to Cities and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, before the Nativity of our Saviour, however you are pleaſed to ſcandalize Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</p>
            <p>It plainly appears alſo that in the heat of your project for this Treatiſe, you either forgot or ſlighted God's Precepts to his people (although you allow of the Scripture) to practice one Religion, and to endeavour the extirpation of all prophaneneſs and falſe worſhip, two unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Conſequences of your good nature and liberty.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not undertake to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine what Church you deſign to defame in your 10.11, 12 and 14th <hi>Pages,</hi> as Author of all the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:175149:14"/>miſeries which have followed the variety of Opinions ſince the Reformation by tying Infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to what they think truth, and Damnation to what ever they think error, but if you intend this Accuſation againſt the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, give me leave to tell you, that it is moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily framed; and it would be an injury to the Proteſtant Principles to deign it any other Anſwer, than to refer the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Practice of our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment both Eccleſiaſtical and Civil, in the ſeveral Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to weak Conſciences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us; and this not only our Laws, but the difference we have ever had with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in that Point makes apparent: A famed Inſtance of which is that of <hi>H.</hi> the Fourth of <hi>France,</hi> whom our Church
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:175149:14"/>loſt upon the account of its Charity in that very Tenent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 14. Another abſurdity (you ſay) your Doctrine is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of, is, That we ſhall not only every one differ from every body elſe, but every one from himſelf: The truth of this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection is evident enough in the various deluſions of the brain ſick Phanaticks, who by following a wrong Guide alſo, their new Light (as they call it) are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily brought into the groſſeſt Abſurdities and Contradictions as well of themſelves as others, both in opinion and practice.</p>
            <p>Now to excuſe the foregoing Abſurdity, and the inconſtancy (as you term it) which will be conſequential to your Doctrine; you make as abſurd and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs a ſuppoſition that thoſe who decline the ſcandal of your way,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:175149:15"/>muſt (on the contrary) be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to a blind and unalterable obſervance of thoſe Laws and Opinions, which either the fate of their Birth and Education, or the fortune of other Accidents, (without any limitation) ſhall engage them in, which may be Ambition, worldly Intereſt, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery, or a pragmatick Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy for a new fangled Treatiſe. To enumerate no more of thoſe unaccountable infirmities and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, which too often influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the frailty of mens minds, who reſiſt Inſtruction, and the Grace of the Holy Spirit, both which are abandoned by your licentious deſign; therefore this Accuſation which you have fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med againſt the Catholick Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, is more applicable to yours than to any other Doctrine in the world.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:175149:15"/>
            <p>But on the other hand, you could not have forged ſo vain a Suppoſition, had you obſerved as you ought, the juſt meaſures of Holy Church, which propoſes nothing to its Votaries but what is both capable and worthy of a rational Aſſent, the beſt <hi>medium</hi> (without doubt) betwixt a blind obedience to Governours, and an abſolute renouncing all Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Example in Affairs of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: Nay ſo wild and unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable are your Poſitions in this Paragraph, that it cannot be denied, but that even a blind Obedience to qualified Guides and Superiours (who are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons more concerned to Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate, and abler to find out the true Religion, than every private man) is much more ſafe and agreeable to Peace and Society, than to ſet up Panaticiſm, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:175149:16"/>by licenſing every one in matters of Religion to gad whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they liſt, like Brutes in Summer ſtung by the various in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſects of their own fancies.</p>
            <p>But in your 16 and 17 <hi>Pages,</hi> you would ſeem ſomething to regulate your foregoing Exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy, by enjoyning your Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples <hi>to make a long and ſerious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, whether they</hi> (I ſuppoſe you mean the former Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) <hi>agree moſt with that light of their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding which God hath infuſed into them for that end, according to the beſt extent of thoſe means which are allowed by him to their underſtandings for this exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</hi> Now according to your ſtyle this may paſs for an imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zel'd deſcription of a compliance with the infuſion of Grace, and plainly ſhews that it is a task too hard for the Natural Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:175149:16"/>of man (upon its own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count) to make ſuch a diſquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which both contradicts and confutes the whole deſign of your Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>It ſeems by your Inſtance of <hi>Chance-medley</hi> in this Paragraph likewiſe, that you are ſubject to miſtakes in the Law, as well as in making of Compariſons, for to ſtate any Fact, <hi>Chance-medley</hi> there muſt be a wilful and raſh, or ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fury or purpoſe for the inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to commit it, which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together omitted, as you have deſcribed the Crime, and makes your Inſtance but <hi>Homicide per infortunium:</hi> Your words are theſe; <hi>And if in this Permutation after all Induſtry and Humility therein, it ſhall be our ill fortune to give away a Truth for a Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, it will be (as killing a man againſt our will, is no murder) at
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:175149:17"/>the worſt but an Error by Chance-medley, and I will both find (I had almoſt ſaid Claim) mercy from God, and Pity from men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But not to inſiſt upon this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, we ſhall examine your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument as you have ſtated your Allegory; <hi>Homicide</hi> by miſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture then, is when any perſon kills a man without malice pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe, foreſight, or any act of his Will, as he is performing ſome lawful Employment; but the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is great, when one man ſhall kill another, after he hath put himſelf into any unwarranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Condition, as an immoderate Fury, Drunkenneſs, and the like; or is exerciſed in any thing that is not allowable by Law, for ſuch previous qualifications, ſtate the ſubſequent Fact voluntary and criminal, which Caſe is parallel to that of your natural Reaſon,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:175149:17"/>when it is employed in matters too high both for its Capacity and Station: What ground have you then (both theſe Inſtances conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered) to be ſo confident of finding or claiming mercy from God, and of deſerving pity from men?</p>
            <p>Your next Argument or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inforcement of your laſt (I know not well which) is another incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Compariſon betwixt Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical Notions, and thoſe in Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, which is regulated and anſwered thus; That (although in unſcholaſtick and common Parleance, a man is ſaid from his birth to his death to be the ſame perſon, becauſe his body all along is informed by the ſame ſoul, yet it is with an allowance during the flux of that time, for his nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental mutation; ſo that we do not Phyſically affirm that every
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:175149:18"/>particle of man's body continues numerically the ſame through all the ſucceſſions of his natural Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, although he hath the ſame Appellation: But when we ſee the body of a man left uninfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and lifeleſs by the departure of his Soul; from that time we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the being of that <hi>Compoſitum</hi> and peculiar denomination to be determined and ceaſe, and if we could perceive the departed Soul, (according to <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) undertake the Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of another body; we ſhould as readily pronounce that to be a new <hi>Compoſitum,</hi> or another per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; this is the caſe of your Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Conſcience (which you call the <hi>Soul of his Faith</hi>) in its tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>migration from the Syſtem or Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the <hi>Proteſtant Faith</hi> to that of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> which from its diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant Articles and Eſſentials to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:175149:18"/>thoſe of our Church, hath been ever diſtinguiſhed by a different Appellation; ſo that theſe two neither in Name nor Eſſence are the ſame Faith, and conſequently if one is true, the other is falſe: therefore I ſhall leave your Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to be informed by your ſelf, after what manner with both theſe Faiths, he ſhall behold his Saviour; and thus you may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve how eaſie it is for you to miſtake an equal Sincerity of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, for an Identity of Faith in your Allegorical Arguments.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Page</hi> 20, to <hi>Page</hi> 26. you employ your confident Guide to aſſert its own Sufficiency by recri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating ours, as not totally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from miſtakes as well as its ſelf, but of the validity of that ſort of arguing, I ſhall leave the Reader to judge, and proceed to the Merits of the Cauſe.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:175149:19"/>
            <p>Thus much then we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that we do not think our ſelves obliged to believe the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors of Holy Church (upon the bare account of Humanity) to be abſolutely infallible, neither do we attribute to them ſo high Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations and Gifts as the firſt planting of the Goſpel did require, and Chriſt's Converſation afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Apoſtles, who likewiſe was not altogether exempt from mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes: but yet we rely upon the Spirit of Truth (which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour promiſed to ſend to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and their Succeſſors after his Aſcenſion) to preſerve them from teaching ſuch Errors as are inconſiſtent with the Divine Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conomy in Affairs of Religion, and the harmony of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>And this in one of your lucid Intervals (<hi>Page</hi> 24.) you in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:175149:19"/>affirm in theſe very ſyllables; <hi>And I verily believe if God had not ſtirred up ſome perſons of excellent Abilities and worthy Spirits (for ſuch ſurely they were, though not exempt from humane weakneſs) to examine by the Rules of their own Reaſons, thoſe Follies and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Errors in Religion, which,</hi> &amp;c. Now in my poor Opinion it will neither blemiſh your ſtyle, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure your Notion to Pen it plainly thus, <hi>If God had not by the aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of his Grace ſtirred up,</hi> &amp;c. For that is the means (according to the Promiſe of our Saviour, and the Tenor of the Scripture) by which God ſtirs up and enables the Minds of men to all religious Performances whether private or publick. I chooſe to anſwer your Recrimination after this manner, rather than to rake into Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, by reviving the exceptions to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:175149:20"/>the Conſtitutions of thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels you quote in this Paragraph, and therefore ſhall ſay no more to this Point, but that our Saviour's not promiſing the ſame meaſure of his Spirit to every private man, as to his Apoſtles and their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, ſtates the right Guides of Holy Church above the ſcandal of your Compariſon, <hi>Page</hi> 25, &amp; 26. You again tell us, that we are in much more danger of being drawn from the Chriſtian Faith, by building our Belief wholly upon the Authority of paſt or preſent Ages, then to remit the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe things to our own Reaſons; in this Aſſertion the term (wholly) altogether excludes a Rational Satisfaction on the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers part, and therefore doth not aſſault the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples for which only I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:175149:20"/>
            <p>You reinforce this Argument againſt the Authority of the Church with another abſurd Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legation, much of the ſame <hi>Claſs</hi> with the former, that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian was neither the moſt ancient nor univerſal Religion in the world: As to the laſt I doubt not but you will agree with us, that immenſe Dominions or vaſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Votaries, are not the inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Characteriſticks of the true Religion; for the greateſt part of the World was inſlaved to <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Gentiliſm,</hi> (as you obſerved) in the time of the Law, as well as of the Goſpel, and you who own the Scriptures muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge with us that the firſt was dictated by God the Father, and the other by his Son, the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Teſtimony for the truth of both.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:175149:21"/>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2ly,</hi> As to the Antiquity of the <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> you cannot but know that the Contents of the Scriptures, and the Conſent of learned men, aſſert the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Goſpel to be laid in the Eternal Decree of a <hi>Meſſias</hi> before the Creation of the World, and that the firſt notice of it here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, was immediately after the Fall of our firſt Parents, when God promiſed a great Redeemer for the Relief of man, who ſhould vanquiſh, and be avenged of the ſubtilty of the Serpent; and after this the Subſtance of the Chriſtian Principles were exiſtent in the Primitive Integrity of <hi>Abel</hi> and his Succeſſors, until the time of <hi>Abraham,</hi> to whom it was revealed that the <hi>Meſſias</hi> ſhould deſcend from his own Loins, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward more particularly to <hi>Jacob,</hi> of what Tribe he ſhould be born.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:175149:21"/>After this manner the Chriſtian Faith was preſerved and conveyed down to the Penning of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and then the Types and Predictions under the Law were the Harbingers of its manifeſtation in the Incarnation, Doctrine, and Miracles of our Saviour, until he ſealed it with his Paſſion: Upon this account you may very well conclude as you do (although againſt your foregoing Allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the ſame Page) that there is more and greater reaſon to be found for the Belief of a Chriſtian, than for any other whatſoever.</p>
            <p>In your 27, &amp; 28 <hi>Pages,</hi> I find ſuch a medley of vile Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as never before was vented by man; for here in your Allegori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Style you take it for granted, that there may be a thouſand right Religions or ways of true Worſhip, although you have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:175149:22"/>the truth of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, which admit but of one.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, That your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Guide by wandring up and down in this multiplicity of Paths, will by a long, troubleſom, and tedious Voyage bring you to happineſs at laſt. Now for the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying this Allegory, you ſhould have made a new Demonſtration, That there are ſo many right ways to Eternal Salvation; otherwiſe if you will meaſure your Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor by the Rules of Holy Writ, it is a thouſand to one but your Guide will deceive you.</p>
            <p>As to the Contents of your 29, 30, 31, &amp; 32 <hi>Page,</hi> I acknowledge that it is not only an Act of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but the abſolute duty of Chriſtians to allow the Gate of Heaven to be as broad as the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures have ſtated it; And on the other ſide, you know the doom
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:175149:22"/>of thoſe who ſhall attempt to preſs it more open than they have ſet it; but in them the Way is ſaid to be ſtreight, and the Gate narrow, and that few ſhall enter therein: Is it not plain therefore, that leaving the right and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing your wrong and natural Guide, you are brought into a ſtreight between two exceſſes? that to ſhun Auſterity (as you term it) on the one ſide, you are put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that profane and wretched belief of an equal poſſibility for the Salvation of <hi>Turks, Heathens,</hi> and <hi>Jews,</hi> with that of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> nay of <hi>Atheists</hi> themſelves, (if there be any ſuch) now if you will believe the Scriptures, <hi>the fool hath ſaid in his heart there is no God.</hi> And amongſt the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then</hi> Philoſophers, not to mention ſingle Inſtances, the whole Sect of the <hi>Epicureans</hi> could be no leſs,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:175149:23"/>who whileſt they could not track the Methods of Divine Power and Providence, denyed the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie's Creation and his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the World.</p>
            <p>After all therefore it ſeems much ſafer to ſuſpend your belief, concerning the Fate of thoſe Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who are out of the Pale of Chriſtianity, and leave them (as you acknowledge ſome do) in the hands of the Creator, than to deſcant (in the leaſt) on his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Diſpoſals not revealed to our Underſtandings.</p>
            <p>But above all, how heretical and horrid is your Conceit about the poſſibility of the Salvation of Devils from the exceſſive kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Judge, which contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts all Divine Declarations? nor is there any colour on their part, to plead either invincible Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or the Merits of a Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:175149:23"/>the two grand means even ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your own Doctrine, for the obtaining of Pardon. Thus you ſee to what extravagancies your Natural Reaſon is brought by a high Conceit and Partiality to its ſelf, under a pretence of Charity to the World.</p>
            <p>As to your Diſcourſe, <hi>Page</hi> 33. That although Chriſt is the onely Source and Cauſe of Eternal Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity, yet you may very well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that there are ſecret and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful ways by which God may be pleaſed to apply his Merits to Mankind, beſides thoſe direct, open, and ordinary ones of <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi> and <hi>Confeſſion;</hi> let it ſuffice thoſe ways are not revealed, and therefore ought not to be pryed into by the Rules of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 34. In defiance of the Churches <hi>Anathemaes,</hi> you aſſert, That all ſorts of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſhall be
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:175149:24"/>ſaved, except their Lives diſagree from their Doctrines, which like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe is a Diſobedience to their Reaſons; and this alſo you in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect have affirmed of men of the worſt Religions, for brevity ſake: Therefore I ſhall endeavour to anſwer them both together, That it is obvious enough, to thoſe who have any inſight into the vaſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences in the profeſſion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity at large, that many paſs under the Title of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they in general profeſs the Miſſion of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> yet hold many Tenents heretical and dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory both to his Nature and Office; and thoſe Opinions (as an additional miſchief) ſo much influence their Actions, that they lead ill Lives ſuitable to the Errors of their Underſtandings: And this alſo is moſt true of the ſtricteſt Profeſſors of the worſt Religions;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:175149:24"/>and it is obſervable that thoſe ſorts of men who after this manner oppoſe the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> and the Precepts of the Scriptures, are ſuch as pay too much Obedience to their Natural Reaſons in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Matters; the Inſtances are too frequent and obvious in all Ages, to need particular Quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 35. Your diſcovery and ſtating of Hereſie is as inſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant as the reſt of your Opinions; for if any one ſhall ſtubbornly ſet up his own private Reaſon and Judgment againſt that of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and ſhall upon that incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent account broach Poſitions contrary to the Principles and Authority of the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> or Practice accordingly: doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs our Eccleſiaſtical Guides in theſe later Ages may pronounce the Cenſures of the Church, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:175149:25"/>ſuch perſons according to the pattern of Primitive Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, who did as little as ours, pretend to the Deities Title of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or as you phraſe it, to have a perfect ſight of the whole Contexture of mens thoughts and actions.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, as to your feigned Law about Murder, and its qualifying Circumſtances to make the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence Conditional, I ſhall only an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that as a Compariſon (at beſt) is no good argument of it ſelf, ſo neither can you deduce any from this for mens diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Church in matters of belief. For the foundation of the Catholique Faith deduced from the Notions and Uſage of Primitive times, backed by the Scriptures, is the higheſt accompt which the nature of the Subject is capable of; therefore whoever it
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:175149:25"/>is propoſed to, may give their ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional aſſent, and is the beſt ground for an unqualified ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence upon all ſtubborn oppoſers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 36. Thus much for Heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy (as you ſay) now for Schiſm; but your way, The remedy for that, is the diſeaſe it ſelf; for Schiſm is defined to be a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary ſeperation from the Church upon a trivial account, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mention either of cenſure or connivance, (the firſt of which you ſay makes, the other cures it) but if this difinition be true, then your individual Sects (however allowed) will be guilty of it after a moſt intolerable manner; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can your abſolute Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency in affairs of Religion, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of any thing more than a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Compliance in mens outward converſation, but utterly ravels that continuity of Faith which is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:175149:26"/>neceſſary to preſerve that unity of the Church you your ſelf mention; nay ſhould ſuch a Licence be but admitted in Temporals, in which Reaſons Plea is much ſtronger to intitle it to an Independency, than in matters of Religion, it will utterly raſe out all Society and Government in them, as all order and communion in Spirituals.</p>
            <p>You endeavour to reinforce this Argument for Independency in Religion, from the great variety which God hath conſtituted in mans material parts &amp; their moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as if he may be delighted with no leſs variety (not only) in mans immaterial Parts, but even in the moſt immaterial Actions of thoſe Parts, the Worſhip and Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Deity, when the very nature of Truth, and the Words of Holy Writ plainly informs us that it can be but one, ſutable
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:175149:26"/>to the unity of the object; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, if a compariſon altogether feigned by a wild ſuppoſition on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (without any demonſtration) betwixt beings of moſt diſſimular natures, may paſs for an Argument, what Propoſition or Truth can be eſtabliſhed among men?</p>
            <p>Page 38. Of what weight or advantage to your Cauſe can you imagine your next Allegation can be; that God (without any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction) receives neither hurt nor advantage from the worſhip of man? when this is a plain truth that his Eſſence (indeed) is not concerned at the operations of the Creature, but his Glory is, as it relates to the Creation, and therefore for the magnifying of that here below, he made man, and inſtituted Divine Worſhip, and hath expreſſed his delight in the uniformity of that devotion which
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:175149:27"/>himſelf hath commanded, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to Truth, and moſt conducible to his Honour, and to the bond of Peace among men; I hope this may convince any one who acknowledges Divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation.</p>
            <p>As to your ſubſequent Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, concerning the uncertainty in the interpretation of Scripture, the Catholique Church declares that the Eſſentials of Faith, and all things of neceſſary obedience, are ſet down poſitively and plainly enough in the Scriptures, for the underſtanding of all ſuch who di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently obſerve them, and make a right uſe of thoſe aides, which God hath prepared for that end. Conſiſtent with this alſo is our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines aſſerting a literal and typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſence, from a ſimple and a compound ſignification of the ſame Text; This latter is appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:175149:27"/>to the Types and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Old Teſtament, which as they were of preſent uſe in the Worſhip of the Jews, ſo it cannot be denyed, but that they had a proſpect and a reference to the coming of our Saviour; And the ſame Text alſo may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in it an Analogical Sence in relation to another, and all this according to the intent of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Unity that penned them; which the ſame Divines will tell you, hath ever been accounted the beſt medium to comprehend, and preſerve the harmony of Holy Writ.</p>
            <p>Your next is ſuch an Argument as was never heard of before. <hi>I ſay that the Commands of God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Religion, are equally obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and fulfilled by all the various kinds of obedience which the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of men conceive themſelves
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:175149:28"/>bound to pay unto them,</hi> how er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous or ſenceleſs ſoever, for ſo your Aſſertion ought to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, as if nonſence and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror were as agreeable to his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Will and Pleaſure, as what is Right and the Truth: Thus while your natural Guide bids defiance to all Authority of others, it ſets up its own, and moſt ſtupidly out-faces God's own Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>In the next place, you would deduce from the Suns melting the Wax, and hardning the Mud; that <hi>Faith is properly one, though according to the divers receptions of it, it produceth not only divers, but contrary effects:</hi> That is, that the ſame Faith may be the Cauſe of Godlineſs, and Profaneneſs, Piety and Irreligion, of the true Worſhip and Idolatry, the own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one God, and Polutheiſm
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:175149:28"/>and Atheiſm, for all theſe lie couched under that futilous So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſm of contrary effects, and your ſuitable ſimilitude of a hard and ſoft temper: but I hope I ſhall not need to Advertiſe any Reader, that theſe inconſiſtent Notions are the effects of your new Humane Reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 40, 41, 42, 43. you Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtically accumulate inveighing Similitudes againſt too auſtere and uncharitable cenſuring of Members infirm or weak in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith; but as they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unapplicable to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods and Tenents of our Church, as hath been made evident; ſo neither are they in the leaſt avail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for the defence of your Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which by an extream on the other hand much more miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous and deſtructive to all
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:175149:29"/>Order in Religion, doth not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of any Cenſures at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 44, &amp; 45. How ever o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as you gueſs (with proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility enough) may accuſe you of Pride and Vanity, for attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſo much to your own reaſon, yet I will not pretend to have ſo clear a ſight into the whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texture of your Thoughts and Actions, as to judge whether it was Pride and Vanity, or humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Charity moſt ſcandalouſly miſtaken, which induced you firſt to embrace, and then to publiſh this Doctrine ſo abſolutely new to the World; but I hope I may (without any tyrannical Aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) let you know that (in my apprehenſion) wiſe men will hardly be perſwaded to allow that for a good natured or peaceable opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which encourageth every one ſtubbornly and inhumanely to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:175149:29"/>undertake to govern himſelf from within in oppoſition to all Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Example, eſpecially ſince the Creator hath inſtituted Subordination and Order, for the prime and original Cement not only of all Societies Celeſtial and Terreſtrial, but alſo of the Fabrick of the material World.</p>
            <p>As for your ſo often reiterated Accuſation of ſuch who claim an Infallibility for their Party, by ſaying, <hi>That who ever is not of my opinion, is in the wrong, and whoever is in the wrong, is to periſh eternally for his Error.</hi> It cannot be at all applyed to the practice of the <hi>Proteſtant Church</hi> (for which I am only concerned) for that ſteers a rational and moderate Courſe betwixt the two Extreams of their Opinion and yours, as hath been manifeſted before.</p>
            <p>But let me remind you alſo,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:175149:30"/>that your Doctrine might more reaſonably deſerve the <hi>Encomium</hi> you give it in this Paragraph, for allowing its Diſciples to lay down an Opinion, when Cauſe ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear for ſo doing, if it did alſo adviſe them to renounce the Guide that brought them into it, which is all the reaſon in the World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 46, &amp; 47. As to your Quarrel with Mr. <hi>Hobbs,</hi> I am not concerned to maintain his Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or to reconcile them with yours, yet (in my weak appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion) you will find it a Task too hard for your Natural Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to make good that Poſition by which you deſign his Defeat: That men ought not to think thoſe Worſhips diſhonourable to God, that are not practiſed by themſelves: For whoever ſhall hold this Aſſertion, muſt either want ſincerity and deceive their
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:175149:30"/>own Souls by practiſing one ſort of Worſhip, and approving of others, or elſe they muſt believe that all ſorts of Worſhip are right which are practiſed among men; or that the Deity equally approves of both the right and the wrong: all which is not only contradictory to Divine Revelation, but alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the Fundamentals and Syſtems of all the Religions in the World, and conſequently your Doctrine, by broaching an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Diſſention amongſt all mortal Votaries, would introduce a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety in Divine Worſhip, more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountably ridiculous than any that ever was heard of in this or former Ages, however you abuſe them.</p>
            <p>In the next place you alledge, <hi>That if ignorant or malicious Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians (in this violent Fever) did not apply new Heats inſtead of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:175149:31"/>they might by Writing, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting, Preaching, and Living Charitably (which is all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer) reduce the World in a ſhort time to its ancient healthful and natural temper:</hi> But what Cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence or Alliance hath the natural temper of the World with its an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and healthful ſtate in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: Therefore to make better ſenſe of this Clauſe we will rectifie it thus; That we allow Writing, Preaching, Diſputing, and living Charitably to be the chief out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward means, as well to Confute Errors in Notion as to reclaim evil Doers, and ſo reduce the Chriſtian World to the Primitive Integrity of Life, and Purity of Doctrine: But let me remind you though, that the Exerciſe and Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of theſe Performances, chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly depend upon Example and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, both which your Doctrine
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:175149:31"/>moſt irrationally diſavows, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can we poſſibly agree with you, that this ancient and health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Temper of the World, was a general Idolatry among the Sons of men; which (within ſix Lines after) you affirm, was the onely Religion for 4000 years: O men! O manners! ſo barbarous Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions was never yet publiſhed by any one who was Maſter of common ſenſe, or had the leaſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight into the Accounts of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane or ſacred Story.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 50, to follow your abrupt, tautological, and prevaricating Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riods, you ſay, you ought not to abſtain from the Chriſtian Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip among <hi>Pagans,</hi> for fear leſt their Mockery and Contempt ſhould on a ſudden (you know not how) Convert it into ſin and blaſphemy; but all ſober Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans will tell you, that if you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:175149:32"/>the true Chriſtian Worſhip amongſt Infidels with ſuch Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Decency, as its own Nature and Principles, and the Circumſtances both of the time and place do require, and they ſhall cauſleſsly deride and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme it, the ſin lies at their own doors, and your endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to promote the Honour of our Saviour, by confeſſing him before men, ſhall be rewarded with his Confeſſing you before his Father that is in Heaven: Thus this Text as well as many more in the Scripture, makes it plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that the ſpreading or advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of the outward Honour of God, doth very much conſiſt in the Opinion of others; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſome Miſcreants by their folly and prophaneneſs may abuſe thoſe things which moſt of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be approved and admired.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:175149:32"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 51, 52. You cannot with any pretence of Reaſon infer from your next inſtance, of the difference betwixt the Capacity of men (who judge thoughts according to outward appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances and actions) and that of the Deity (wholly an exertion of his Omniſcience, without any mediate and extrinſick means) perfectly knows the Hearts of all Men; that outward Worſhip is of ſo little concernment to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, that men may perform it by any Rituals or Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies whatſoever; or to uſe your own words, <hi>they would find no more hurt from the uſe of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Ceremonies</hi> (without any li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation) <hi>than of different Tongues in the ſame City.</hi> Now the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of this inference is ſo immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt and impious, that I dare not quote particular inſtances to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:175149:33"/>quaſh and confute it, but adviſe you to recollect your ſelf from theſe Generals. Firſt, that the chief end of Divine Worſhip here below, is the magnifying Gods Honour in the Rational world, for which purpoſe he hath diſtinguiſhed mans Duty, from Crimes; Piety, from Vice; Prayers and Allelujahs, from Curſing and Blaſphemy, and words and geſtures (of which External Worſhip conſiſts) are Characterized accordingly, as out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward evidences of both: Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever therefore ſhall dare to uſe Blaſphemous, or obſcene Speeches or Actions, in the Worſhip of the Deity (which will undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly come to paſs, when the Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble are let looſe to Natural Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for their guide, as the Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the Gentiles have ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently manifeſted) muſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:175149:33"/>become <hi>Anathema</hi> to him, and a much worſe <hi>Barbarian</hi> to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Congregations, than he that ſpeaks in an unknown Tongue, which you ſo juſtly Condemn as a Phantaſtical Uſage in the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the <hi>Papists.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, I cannot but admire, that Gods own Preſcription of a Ceremonial Law in the Theocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the <hi>Jews,</hi> as well as the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Uſage of Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, doth not above all things Convince you, that a conſent in outward decency is both harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious and neceſſary in Divine Worſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 53. I had almoſt forgot one of your Metaphorical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances: <hi>As words are the Images of our thoughts, ſo our thoughts are of the things themſelves, &amp; as well may differing thoughts truly repreſent the Worſhip of one God and his Son Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:175149:34"/>Chriſt, as differing words can repreſent the ſame thoughts.</hi> Not to create a Prolixity, by a ſtrict Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of all the plain defects in this Compariſon, let it ſuffice to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mind you, that if mens practices in Adoration, ſhall be agreeable to their ſeveral, and unaccountable apprehenſions and belief of a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity (which you require in your Diſciples) then the Worſhips of one God (for they cannot be the ſame) will be as different and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious, as the injudicious and unbridled fancies of all the ſorts of men can poſſibly invent, and how ſuitable ſuch a Confuſion of Worſhips can be to the Nature and Purity of the only true God, I leave the Reader to judge.</p>
            <p>In the next place, If the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of learned men, or the plain words of the Text are to be credited, your taking humane
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:175149:34"/>Reaſon for a Guide in matters too high for it, is the ſame Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour with that of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> which St. <hi>Paul</hi> bids ſo high a defy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to, in the beginning of his firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians;</hi> where upon the account of Grace, ſupernaturally infuſed into his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts by the Divine Spirit, enabling him to apprehend and believe the myſtery of Chriſts In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation and Paſſion, altogether hid from the beſt and cleareſt humane Reaſon (as you well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, <hi>page</hi> 57.) he Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns the Natural, Moral, and Political knowledge of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, Orators, and Princes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and ſeems upon that account to call it the Wiſdom of the Princes of the World, which plainly evinces, that he intended this accuſation againſt humane Wiſdom in its trueſt State, as it
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:175149:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>was different from the Spiritual knowledge of the Goſpel, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to them that the things which are not, that is, of no value amongſt them <hi>viz.</hi> the Doctrine of the Goſpel, ſhould confound the thing that are, that is moſt highly eſteemed by them, which was humane Reaſon in its vigour as it was poſſeſſed by thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons great and learned in their generations, as their Writings make manifeſt even to this day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 58. Againſt the common Principles of Chriſtianity you aſſert, that for the diſcovery of Divine Truths, Grace did not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Eye-ſight of Humane Reaſon, but only draw the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject nearer to it. Now the falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of this Opinion will in ſome meaſure appear. Firſt by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining your aſſertion upon a natural account, in which expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:175149:35"/>informs you, that the near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er thoſe Objects approach whoſe appearances are too intenſe for the reception of the Organ, the more they dazle and confound, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of being diſcerned, as they are by the unqualified Optick, the exact ſtate of your Humane Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in this Caſe, according to the beſt Chriſtian Principles.</p>
            <p>But <hi>2ly,</hi> A more apt and genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine Confutation of your Error, may be drawn from your own ſubſequent Inſtance of the new ſtate of things, which ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed at the ſecond Coming of our Saviour; when our mortal Capacity ſhall receive ſuch a qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification and change, as ſhall enable it to behold and ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Grand Appearance: And in Analogy to this, as his Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotence then will make a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parative Change, for the ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:175149:36"/>of our Nature, at that moſt high and amazing Tribunal, ſo he adminiſters his Grace now for the illuminating of our Minds, to apprehend and embrace his Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual manifeſtation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 59. Notwithſtanding your great pretence to a peaceable al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of every man's Opinion in matters of Religion, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forbear Carping at, and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to Correct the Tranſlation of the Bible, but altogether with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Cauſe; for whoever Conſults the Text will find, that <hi>Animalis</hi> there ſignifies <hi>à divinis alienus,</hi> and ſo is intended of the rational man, and is diſtinguiſhed from <hi>ſenſualis,</hi> as, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and this, Commentators upon the place, affirm to be agreeable to the Context, the moſt approved way for ſtating Controverted Scriptures.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:175149:36"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 61. To juſtifie your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer miſtake of the Scriptures, you hazard another, by affirming that when the Apoſtle ſpeaks of his fighting <hi>with Beaſts at Epheſus,</hi> he means Diſputations with ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual men; but certainly you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ignorant, that you have conſiderable <hi>Antagoniſts</hi> in this Point alſo, who underſtand the Place according to the Letter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe to be expoſed to <hi>wild beasts,</hi> was a puniſhment in thoſe times, to which the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorably ſubject, from whence the Outcry upon any publick Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, <hi>Chriſtiani ad leones:</hi> Beſide, whether the words literally under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, ſhall be interpreted to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in them a direct Affirmation, that he had really fought; or as a Suppoſition only, if, or in caſe he had <hi>fought with beaſts at Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> (of which he might have been in
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:175149:37"/>ſome hazard at leaſt, and as ſome think was prevented by his Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates) they are alledged to be either way more forcible to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, what the Apoſtle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to prove at that time, his belief of the Reſurrection, than if they ſhall be underſtood of a Metaphorical Combate. I only hint this to remind you how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitable this Magiſterial and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>papricious Project is to your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of an univerſal peaceable li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and that you may collect from your own miſcarriages in laying the Plot, what is likely to prove the common fate of your Diſciples.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 62. You would be at your Victory both ways again; I ſhall tranſpoſe your words, but not vary the ſenſe: That it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for Humane Reaſon to loſe any thing in one place, without
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:175149:37"/>gaining as much in ſome other; for by our Reaſons being guided, conquered, and inſlaved, theirs are become Guides, Conquerors, and Maſters; which when they have done, then they will loſe what they contend for: But you here forget that ſuch a Conqueſt cannot be made upon ſo impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Principles; and on the other ſide, if this Suppoſition could be made an Experiment, that way alſo your uncontroulable liberty will be utterly quaſhed, which is all we contend for. Nay, had you well weighed the Contents of your foregoing Paragraph, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> by true reaſon overcame and captivated the falſe ones, and that by right of Conqueſt, you muſt neceſſarily have ſeen in this Aſſertion as ſtrong an Argument, as can be for Example and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity grounded upon reaſon, which
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:175149:38"/>might happily have prevented your publiſhing to the World ſo many Impertinencies and Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, as are contained in this Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>In the next place you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to fortifie your Project with three Arguments (as you ſtyle them) but they are rather Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tologies, for they are nothing more in effect than the former Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions in other Similies and Phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; but I will curſorily examine them for full ſatisfaction: Your firſt Argument, like the <hi>Trojan</hi> Horſe, contains in its Bowels ſix monſtrous Reaſons to make good the Combate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 63. For your firſt Reaſon you aver, that we have no more warrantable ground for our Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Authority, than the <hi>Fanaticks</hi> and <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> have for following the <hi>Ignis fatuus</hi> of their
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:175149:38"/>own brains, or that of evil Spirits; and that our happening into the right by following it, is meerly good fortune, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but if you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend this Derogation againſt the Authority of the Church, deduced upon a rational account from the Contents of Holy Writ and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive uſage, as it hath been ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before, then I doubt not but all ſober men will agree, that you ought with much more juſtice and correſpondence to your own Conceſſions, have compared their pragmatick and haughty Preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions to that of your own Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; for you have acknowledged that your Guide as well as theirs, will lead its followers into Errors; but to ſolve this <hi>Phoenomenon,</hi> you are reduced moſt abſurdly to give us your ſingle Authority, that the Errors of you and your Guide are ſafe, but theirs unpardonable; but
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:175149:39"/>it hath already been made good againſt you, that your Guide, as well as theirs, ingages in an Office without any warrant, which makes the Errors on both parts conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quential to that Aſſumption e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually blameable.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2ly,</hi> To reinforce this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, you quote <hi>Eves</hi> pleading the Authority of the Serpent, and <hi>Adam</hi> hers, yet all were puniſhed; but this Inſtance is as unapplicable as their Pleas were unwarrantable, and plainly ſhews that your Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is ſo far from being a good Guide in Divine matters, that it is an ill one in common ſence; for the degrees of that Seduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment riſing by a <hi>Climax,</hi> (the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour all along influencing the ſuperiour) is the method of true Authority abſolutely reverſt: but I admire alſo that you did not correct your Error, by conſulting
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:175149:39"/>the Text, <hi>The woman that thou ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt</hi> (not to be over me but) with me, as the expreſſion in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> imports.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 65. You as abſurdly give us again your own Affirmation only, That the followers of your Guide, if they commit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wholly to it, are as ſafe in their Errors as others are in em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing the truth; and whether it takes its Voyage to the <hi>Artick</hi> or <hi>Antartick,</hi> to the left, or the right, it will bring them to the wiſhed end of their Journey, Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs at laſt; as if Errors and what is falſe, were <hi>Mediums</hi> as ſafe and prevalent, as the Truth for the obtaining of Bliſs, which contradicts the general <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of the World and the Natural and Common Reaſon of all Men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 66. After a moſt imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:175149:40"/>imbezelling both of Words and Senſe, you at laſt aſſert; <hi>Now He</hi> (that is God) <hi>that bids you ſearch, is cruel and barbarous in his mockery, if he knoweth you have no power or faculty ſo to ſearch as he commands you, there is therefore in man a natural ability of ſearching ſpiritual Truths.</hi> Now as your Suppoſition is groundleſs, ſo is your <hi>Concluſion,</hi> and directly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to a Poſition of your own, that natural reaſon of it ſelf ſeeth neither the <hi>what,</hi> nor the <hi>how</hi> of Spiritual Verities: Therefore as I have demonſtrated before, God hath ordained and adminiſtred means peculiarly appropriate to the Condition of every Age, for the enabling the Humane Faculty to ſearch according to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, much better than it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly can upon the ſcore of lapſed Nature, which fully acquits him
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:175149:40"/>of your blaſphemous Suppoſition, and ſhews you the falſhood of your Hetrodox Aſſumption.</p>
            <p>Your ſecond Reaſon hath been often confuted before; for your Natural Reaſons, ſetting it ſelf up for a Guide in matters too high for it, in that commits an error, which otherwiſe is avoidable; and upon that ſcore alſo cannot poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly make a ſearch that is truly mature, which gives a juſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation to the Deity, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn ſuch ill Beliefs and ill Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as proceed from that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption.</p>
            <p>In your third Reaſon, you are at your large Principles of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty again, for the Salvation of all, who have the fortune to be Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers, which hath I hope been ſufficiently ſpoken to in the whole Series of theſe Remarks, and therefore needs no other anſwer.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:175149:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>As to your fourth Reaſon, if your Conſidering-men in that will but obſerve what Errors in Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief are conſequential to this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of their Natural Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and ſuch others which ariſe (as this doth) from the Depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of the Will, it will ſerve them for a Catalogue of all Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours that are damnable, and prove very inſtrumental to help them to find out Salvation.</p>
            <p>As to your fifth Reaſon, a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Obſervation alſo of this plain diſtinction of Errors, into wilful and unwilful, joyn'd with a general Compunction for ſuch as are unobſerved or forgotten (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Principles of the Catholick Church) I will at once take off that vain Imputation of Cruelty which you would lay up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God, and alſo cure your own pretended Incapacity to repent,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:175149:41"/>for want of a knowledge of your faults, by clearing to your Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, what Actions or Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefs are truly Culpable, which will direct your Devotion to the proper Subjects for Repentance.</p>
            <p>As to your moſt vain Objection in your ſixth Reaſon, concerning Man's Incapacity to find out the Truth, as it hath been fully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered before, ſo it can have no other Fund, beſide that impious and colluding Doctrine of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability framed by the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> to patronize a Sinners living in ſin: Your own words are theſe; — <hi>If that be probable which all, or moſt men, or many, or the moſt wiſe, or ſome wiſe men receive for truth, what Doctrine is there which in the whole Compaſs of Religions, may not paſs for probable.</hi> But for a ſhort Anſwer to this. If there be ſo great a probability of erring by
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:175149:42"/>following wiſe men; how much more liable are the Ignorant then to erre, when left to their own Conduct?</p>
            <p>As to your ſecond Argument, to avoid tediouſneſs, I ſhall not examine all thoſe defective and incongruous Inſtances in the firſt part of it, becauſe ordinary Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities may diſcover their being unapplicable, as well as untrue, by their own experience; but to ſhun the Cenſure of affirming this <hi>Gratis,</hi> I ſhall hint at one of them, <hi>viz.</hi> The ſeeming Crookedneſs of a ſtreight Stick, part in the Air, and part in the Water, the ſtreight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of which may be diſcovered by an Appeal to the Touch, but I ſhall proceed to the Objection which you make againſt them your ſelf; for if that can be made good againſt your own Anſwer, it will moſt genuinely confute the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:175149:42"/>whole Paragraph, you object thus; <hi>That the ſight though it be ſubject to ſome particular Impediments, yet it is generally by its own nature much more certain and exact in the judgment of Colours, than the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding can ever be made (even without accidental hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances) in the knowledge of things ſpiritual.</hi> Your Anſwer to it is this; <hi>That if ſuch things are the proper Objects of ſuch a Faculty, we are herein to be governed by the Dictates of it, without conſidering whether that Faculty be as quick and perfect as God could make it in Apprehenſion of its Objects, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought we to give leſs truſt to our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderstanding in ſupernatural Truths, becauſe it is ſo much infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to that of Angels, than we do to our Eye-ſight in things viſible, though it be ſo far ſhort of that of Eagles.</hi> Briefly that which makes
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:175149:43"/>your Objection too ſtrong for your Anſwer, is that Angelical Intuition, &amp; Truths ſupernatural, are of the ſame ſtate, and ſo alſo is the Eye-ſight and viſible Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects here below (although the Organs of Creatures may be dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently qualified for, as well as improved by, the different occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their lives) but our natural Underſtanding, and Spiritual Things or Truths Supernatural, are not of the ſame ſtate, and therefore in a true ſence cannot be ſaid to be its proper Objects, which evinces that it needs Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural Helps to enable it to apprehend them: I would gladly here have ended my Anſwer to this Argument; but that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but remind you of a groſs failance in your Memory, for you formerly, in effect, affirmed, that the Worſhip of man is of no
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:175149:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>Concern to the Deity. But here <hi>Page</hi> 76. You tell us, that when God had Created all things elſe, he thought the World im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect as yet, whileſt there was nothing made that could Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template, Thank and Worſhip the Maker of it, which plainly ſtates the Worſhip of Man to be of high Concern both to the Creation, and the Creator: But you imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to theſe Premiſſes joyn a moſt incongruous Concluſion, that the mannners and kinds of doing it are accidental; but cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly you cannot hope to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade any rational man (when all means are proportioned to their ends by the order of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe) that ſo conſiderable an end ſhould have ſuch inconſiderable ways to it; or that the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and its reward ſhould be like no other valuable thing, or
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:175149:44"/>end in the World, to be utterly deſtitute of all certain Rules and Means to attain them: Therefore I ſhall leave this Clauſe to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dargution of the Satyriſt, <hi>Deſinit in piſcem mulier formoſa ſuperne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your third Argument to gain your Opinion an allowance in the World, is an Affirmation, that it is not only moſt ſafe, and moſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural for every man in particular, but likewiſe moſt agreeable to the good and intereſt of Humane Society: for all Wars of late ages have been, either really for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion (or at leaſt) that hath been one of the chief Pretences, which if it were quite taken away, it would be difficult for thoſe men who diſguiſe their ambition with it, to draw the People into the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries and uncertainties either of a civil or a foreign War; but it had been very requiſite that you
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:175149:44"/>ſhould have explain'd your ſelf here, whether you would have the pretence of fighting for it, or Religion it ſelf quite taken away; for not only this Clauſe, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed your whole Treatiſe ſeems to aim at that end; for if all Forms and Ligaments of any Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies whether Eccleſiaſtical or Civil ſhall be deſtroyed and broken, their Fabricks muſt fall, and this the admittance of your unlimited Liberty will effect in the <hi>Syſtems</hi> of all the Governments and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions eſtabliſhed in the World.</p>
            <p>But to paſs by this <hi>Peccadillo,</hi> and to come to the body of your Argument, if Unity in Religion will produce a general Amity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men, which you ſeem to acknowledge, <hi>Page</hi> 79. then the nearer the Conſtitution of the Univerſe approaches to this Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the fewer occaſions will ariſe
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:175149:45"/>of Diſcord and War; and on the contrary, when Differences in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſhall be unaccountable and numberleſs, they will conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adminiſter many more oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities for Ambitious and turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent men (and ſuch you confeſs there will be among the Herd of your Libertines) to engage the People in Blood and War; ſo that except you were endued with a Power to change the lapſed Nature of Man, you will never find ſo good natured Diſciples as to practiſe your Doctrine peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably in this ſtate.</p>
            <p>Your laſt defence of this Clauſe which (you ſay <hi>Pag.</hi> 80.) needs not the aſſiſtance of any other (in my poor Opinion) is a plain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion of it; for although at firſt, you as vainly as confidently aſſert, <hi>That it is impoſſible that ever any man ſhould have been, is, or can be
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:175149:45"/>hereafter guided by any thing elſe, but his own reaſon, as in other things, ſo in matters of Religion:</hi> Yet when you come to prove this, you preſently fall into the Toyls of a threefold Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (theſe are your words) <hi>For whatſoever way we take, we ſhall find, that the laſt Element into which our Faith is reſolved (and therefore it is compounded of the ſame) is only reaſon.</hi> (I omit your Inſtance of an Anchor as one of your Allegorical Tautologies) but ſhall ſhew you your Abſurdities in your moſt material Metaphor and its terms. Firſt then, if your Reaſon is only a ſingle Element or Ingredient, of which among others, our Faith is compounded, by what Logick can you ſtate it our ſole and infallible Guide with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any thing elſe in matters of Religion? Secondly, If to avoid
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:175149:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>this, you ſhall alledge that our Faith is compounded of our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon alone, as of one ſingle Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment only, then (according to all the Rules of reaſoning and ſenſe) this is no Compoſition. Thirdly, Neither can the parts of this notional Compoſition be ſo reſolved into one elemental laſt, as to enable it to perform the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the whole; for if the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition be good, every part hath its uſe, and therefore to ſupport it, muſt be of equal duration; but you might have been convinced of theſe Vanities alſo by the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent Series or Compoſition of our Faith, which you have ſet down in a tedious Catalogue of Syllogiſtical Fragments.</p>
            <p>As to the other part of this Clauſe; true it is, Rationality not being wholly extinguiſhed by the Fall of our firſt Parents, Man
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:175149:46"/>ſtill is capable of living eternally, but its perſpicacity and vigour is ſo much impaired by it, that Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Reaſon is become dim-ſight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all things; but eſpecially in thoſe matters of Religion, which you ſtyle <hi>Celeſtial Myſteries</hi> and <hi>Verities</hi> (as Objects too high for it) and therefore even according to the terms of your own notion, as well as Humane Reaſon's beſt Meaſures, it needs proportionable helps to enable it to underſtand and acquieſce in their Truths.</p>
            <p>Now after my beſt examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I can find no ground why you ſhould boaſt of this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, except it be for your dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity, in packing up two or three Contradictions in the ſame Clauſe; therefore to end all De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates concerning this Point, I ſhall leave the Reader to judge whether it looks like the laſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:175149:47"/>or the laſt Gaſp of your Cauſe.</p>
            <p>The purport of your next Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion in this Paragraph, is, that no Authority is obeyable or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievable of it ſelf without further examination; that is, without a rational account which no <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi> denieth.</p>
            <p>You extravagantly tell us in the next place, that our Reaſon not only preſcribes Obedience and Belief to us, but alſo ſearcheth and eſtabliſheth the bounds of both, ſetting up ſome ſolid and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Notions, by which we know our <hi>ne plus ultra:</hi> Now the beſt ſenſe that I can make of this my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical <hi>Periphraſis</hi> is, that we muſt obey and believe upon a rational account, which we aſſert all along; but if you have any further aim beſide this, I aſſure you that the not appearing of your apparent
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:175149:47"/>Notions, puts a <hi>ne plus ultra,</hi> as well to my Underſtanding, as my Deſign of anſwering them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 86. In this ſhort Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph you promiſe to omit, that is, as I hoped, not to trouble us with that which by a breach of your Promiſe you make the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of your next: but it had been much more Civility and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to have performed your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement; for it is only a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilation or Summary of all the grand Errors that lie diſperſed in your Treatiſe, and ſeems to be chiefly compoſed out of your old <hi>Pieque</hi> to <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> to inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate over again, that the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion</hi> wants both Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and Univerſality for its Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification: All which hath been diſcuſſed in the foregoing Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks, and is but a beating the Air, or rather a return <hi>Cum ſuae
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:175149:48"/>ad volutabrum;</hi> therefore I ſhall chooſe to joyn iſſue with you up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſufficiency of my former Anſwers, rather than by a need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and tedious rehearſal to nauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the Reader.</p>
            <p>By this time poſſibly it may appear, that fewer Arguments might have been ſufficient to have anſwered your whole Treatiſe, but I thought it requiſite to examine it throughly (although forced in ſome places to a repetition of things, by following your Tauto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies) leſt that thin Vail of an Allegorical Style, and incompe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Similies (which you have all along ſpread over the many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formities both of your Arguments and Doctrine) ſhould in ſome place or other deceive the inarti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial reaſonings of ordinary ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, for whoſe ſake only it deſerves an Anſwer.</p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:175149:48"/>
            <p>And now I have finiſhed my task of examining the validity of the particular Objections and Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments contained in your Treatiſe, I ſhall for a Cloſe give you a Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary (as well as I can) of the grand defects both of your Doctrine and Deſign.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, you have not dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted your Diſcourſe to the moſt proper and adaequate Subject of the Title prefixt to your Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2ly,</hi> By ſtating Humane Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the ſole Judge of and Guide to the true Religion, you have attributed to that (whoſe Office it is to be only ſubſervient as a Miniſter to our Faith) the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Court of Appeal and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Judicatory, as well concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the true Religion it ſelf, as all Methods and means of finding it out, and yet (ſo unfortunate
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:175149:49"/>are you) that many of your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions plainly oppoſe it, as hath been made evident.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3ly,</hi> According to your Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of an Unlimited Liberty, theſe Guides will prove rather numberleſs than one, for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Humane Reaſon is of ſo different degrees in the minds of Individuals, that no two perſons in the world do entirely acquieſce in the ſame intrinſick Standard and Rule of their Thoughts and Opinions, and yet every man's ſearch muſt be according to his Capacity.</p>
            <p>Theſe Guides (for ſo we muſt call them) you (upon the ſcore of your own authority) affirm, will conduct their Followers through Errors to the true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and its reward, Eternal Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs at laſt; which Errors (ſo unlimited and barbarous is your
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:175149:49"/>Doctrine) may be <hi>Idolatry, Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm, Blaſphemy,</hi> &amp;c. to which Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Reaſon hath already led great part of the world, as you have obſerved; although it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denied, but that the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> were indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it in a high degree, as their Writings make manifeſt.</p>
            <p>And as you have not ſtated what ſize and degree of Humane Reaſon (whileſt ſo many are exerciſed) is to be pitched upon, for this ſo infallible, yet erring Guide; ſo neither have you gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us any good definition or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the true Religion, nor any the leaſt aſſurance that you your ſelf have been led to it by your own Guide: For although we may poſſibly ſuppoſe (by a Charity not much unlike that which you have for the Devils) that you may be ſome ſort of
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:175149:50"/>Chriſtian by your Cheveril Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of Chriſtianity at large, yet ſuch a looſe Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not diſtinctive enough to point out the true Religion, from thoſe that are erroneous, in regard many who generally own (with you) the Miſſion of our Saviour, hold Doctrines derogatory both to his Office and Nature.</p>
            <p>In fine therefore, I am apt to believe, that your Readers will only agree with you in this Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition (againſt the reſt of the Treatiſe) <hi>That we have great need of a beter Eye-ſight than is left us by the Fall of our firſt Forefather, to direct us in this ſearch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I bid you adieu.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:175149:50"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> Poſtſcript, <hi>or</hi> Appendix.</head>
            <p>AFter the preceding <hi>Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement</hi> and <hi>Remarks</hi> had layn by me ſometime wholly fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed as they are, there came to my hands (in <hi>March</hi> laſt) a Tract Intituled, <hi>An Apologie for the Diſcourſe of Humane Reaſon,</hi> Written by <hi>Mat. Clifford,</hi> Eſq; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>Reply</hi> to <hi>Plain Dealing,</hi> which I never heard of until then: In which the <hi>Apologizer</hi> declares, That he writ this Defence at Mr. <hi>Clifford</hi>'s requeſt (who died ſoon after) If ſo, then I ſuppoſe the firſt deſigned to publiſh the <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> and the other the <hi>Apologie,</hi> as
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:175149:51"/>their laſt Wills and Teſtaments; In which they have bequeathed to the World a Confuſion of <hi>Common Sence,</hi> and of all <hi>Method</hi> and <hi>Rules</hi> of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimity</hi> and <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der:</hi> Therefore after I had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed it, I thought it more ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and requiſite than ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to publiſh theſe <hi>Remarks,</hi> (if they may haply) contain in in them any thing advantageous to the Truth, or the Vindication of our Religion, which I ought to refer to the Cenſure of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudiced Reader.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not trouble either him or my ſelf, to run another Wild-Gooſe Chaſe after all the Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars contained in this <hi>Apologie,</hi> as I have done heretofore, after thoſe of the <hi>Treatiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, In regard this <hi>Reply</hi> is directed to another man's <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:175149:51"/>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2ly,</hi> I hope that the Impartial Reader may find all Arguments material for the Defence of the <hi>Treatiſe</hi> anticipated in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks;</hi> therefore I ſhall but cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorily touch upon ſome very few Paſſages in this <hi>Reply,</hi> which did not fall under my Province before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 3. I humbly conceive that the <hi>Apologiſt</hi> is miſtaken, in which he affirms, that his Author's Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition amounts to no more, than that <hi>every man muſt follow right Reaſon, which is his direct way:</hi> For his Author, <hi>Page</hi> 2. declares, <hi>That after a long and ſerious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate about a Guide, that Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration brought no other to him, beſides his own Reaſon.</hi> Now I hope he will not lift up his cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated Author ſo high above the ſtate of Humanity, as to aſſert that he is endued with the Gift
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:175149:52"/>of right Reaſon, or that by uſing ſuch Care and Conſtancy only, as is within the power of his own Reaſon; he is able to follow or exert that which is ſo much above it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 34. The <hi>Apologist</hi> uſes this expreſſion; <hi>Mine own Reaſon that is my Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Page</hi> 73. His words are theſe; <hi>Every Humane Excellency reſolves into Reaſon, or ſhrouds un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der its <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbrage, Reaſon, which (as a light Divine) governed the World before that Metaphorical word</hi> Conſcience <hi>was known.</hi> But how ſhall we underſtand or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile theſe two places? for if he intends here, that right Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is his Conſcience, by which the Deity (indeed) did govern the World before Conſcience was named, and likewiſe ever ſince; then all ſober men will inform
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:175149:52"/>him, that his Reaſon, or his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, whether he fancies them to be one, or diſtinct, cannot be of the ſame ſtate with that of the <hi>Deities;</hi> ſo that this Notion muſt prove but a Phanatick <hi>Chimera</hi> of his own Brain: But if on the other hand he means that lapſed Reaſon is his Conſcience, then (how young ſoever the Name is) Conſcience it ſelf is as old as that, and Tranſgreſſion; witneſs the Fear and the Shame of our firſt Parents in Paradice.</p>
            <p>To theſe two Contradictions, we may add another in this Caſe, <hi>Page</hi> 136. the ſum of it is this, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out varying the ſenſe, <hi>Conſcience</hi> is more ſubject to Errour than <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and that <hi>Reaſon</hi> (to ſpeak humanely) muſt be the elder; if ſo, then with full as good ſenſe it may be ſaid, He ſpeaks inhumane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly who aſſerts they are the ſame.</p>
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:175149:53"/>
            <p>But not to leave weak Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities betrayed thus to Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Offices of Reaſon and Conſcience are generally diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; for by the firſt, we exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and underſtand the nature and ſtate of all Acts whatſoever, that fall under the Cognizance of our rational Faculty; and as to ſuch as relate to Innocence and Guilt, Conſcience by a diſtinct and ſuperadded reflection, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns or approves of their omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or performance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 46. The firſt part of this <hi>Paragraph</hi> is touched on before in the <hi>Remarks;</hi> the ſecond Part is an Argument with two handles, the ſum of it is this; If <hi>Luther</hi> had not followed his own Reaſon, the Reformation (in all humane pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability) had not been effected; for either it was Reaſon which ſatisfied him then, and his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:175149:53"/>ever ſince, or they are all unreaſonable; your Concluſion is ſomething too quick: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us examine the force of this Argument by turning the Tables (if you pleaſe) by this Rule then; If <hi>Luther</hi> was guided by Humane Reaſon in his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſo to the right Religion (and that ours is ſo you have not hitherto denied) then thoſe that ſtayed behind muſt be endued with little or none of it, which no wiſe man (with reverence to your parts) will ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to affirm; for the great worldly Policy, and outward Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of that Church in its ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, makes it evident enough, that many of its Members did then, and their Succeſſors now, do poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs as great a ſhare of Humane Reaſon, as <hi>Luther</hi> himſelf, which (to ſtop all your Muces) muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:175149:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>have put them upon as ſtrict an exertion of diligence and enquiry upon a natural ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count only, as <hi>Luther</hi>'s did him: according to your own Principle, that the Will irreſiſtably follows the laſt dictates of the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. I doubt here your Natural or Humane Reaſon is in ſuch an extricable ſtreight, that it muſt be relieved by this Orthodox So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution; <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Luther</hi>'s Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in this work did ſubmit to the guidance of more ſublime Aids which enlighten'd and fortified his Spirit againſt thoſe Seduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Corruptions which theirs did embrace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 66. The <hi>Apologiſt</hi> pretends that he cannot apprehend what Ignorance can be wilful, nor what is free Will, <hi>the Will always follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and being acted by the laſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding.</hi> To the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:175149:54"/>firſt, I ſhall anſwer him briefly, That whoever is negligent to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form himſelf in any matter, that it is his duty to know, his Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance conſequential to that neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, the <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> (from the nature of the Cauſe) term vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible and voluntary: but here it is obſervable, that the <hi>Apologiſt</hi> proves a very treacherous Second, by turning his Point upon his Principal, who allows of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction in ſeveral places of his <hi>Treatiſe:</hi> And as to his denying the freedom or rather the liberty of the <hi>Will;</hi> becauſe as he alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, it always follows, and of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity is acted by the laſt Dictate of the Underſtanding: He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers it in this <hi>Paragraph,</hi> by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting himſelf in theſe very ſyllables, <hi>Men cannot therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what they pleaſe, nor think what they pleaſe that ſuch or ſuch
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:175149:55"/>an opinion or thing, is true or falſe. Indeed a man may act contrary to his understanding which is hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, and which if the Gent. plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, he may call wilful hypocriſie.</hi> And he, if he pleaſes, may likewiſe take notice that this act of <hi>hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie,</hi> which he ſaith, is contrary to mens underſtandings, whilſt ſuch mens judgments and perſwaſions diſallow of their practice, muſt be an effect of, and can have no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe, than the freedoom or liberty of the <hi>Will:</hi> But if he be unwilling to be Convicted from his own contradiction, I refer him to the words of the Sorcereſs in <hi>Ovid.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Video meliora proboque,</l>
               <l>—Deteriora ſequor.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 82. He gives (as he fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieth) ſage Counſel to the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, by adviſing them not to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with the Government in the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:175149:55"/>Pulpit, but forgot to obſerve it himſelf, in Compoſing this <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> in which he hath made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pert and bold Eſſays, to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh our Governors (like an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt,</hi> or a <hi>Pagan</hi>) to ſuffer our Religion to truckle to our Trade, by hinting that the <hi>Phanaticks,</hi> as a Pack of formidable <hi>Heroes,</hi> ſhould not be diſturbed; but Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence informs us, That the due ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of our Laws, will prove this Pretence to be as groundleſs and falſe, as the reſt of his <hi>Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie:</hi> however we will agree with him, That the direful ſparks which heretofore have ſet the Kingdom in a flame, have flown from the Pulpit, as well as from Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 84. He Combates his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal again in theſe words; <hi>I think it is beſt to be of the Religion of a man's Country externally:</hi> (He
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:175149:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>means hypocritically) <hi>at leaſt; and ſure I am, there is nothing morally evil in ours: and for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Worſhip in Religion, as to time and place, it is determinable by the Supream Magiſtrate.</hi> But, how can this be Conſiſtent with the Fundamental Doctrine of the Text (as he ſtyles it) that every one ought to have leave to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern himſelf from within, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any regard to Example or Authority, or any thing elſe; there can be no <hi>Salvo</hi> for this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, but that he being a very great Wit, may have a very ill memory.</p>
            <p>In the next place, I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge I cannot make ſenſe of this Expreſſion, Page 92. <hi>I mean all</hi> Proteſtants <hi>of what Species ſoever here in</hi> England. For how can thoſe Votaries who differ ſpecifically in their Worſhip and Religion, be
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:175149:56"/>comprehended under the ſame Denomination; our Laws alſo owning but one ſort of <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> as agreeable to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the true <hi>Proteſtant</hi> or <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> whoſe Members are obliged to hold and confeſs the ſame Doctrine and Faith, and to be of the ſame Communion; but (it ſeems) you have found out ſome <hi>Centaures</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> who have coined a new Name for themſelves very ſuitable to this Fiction; <hi>viz. Proteſtant Diſſenters,</hi> a Title very agreeable alſo to the reſt of their and your Notions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Contradiction in terms.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus much for your Apologie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I come to your <hi>Review</hi> and <hi>Appendix,</hi> made upon ſo long Conſideration; wherefore I did expect in it an abſolute Retracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or at leaſt a general amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:175149:57"/>of the vain and impertinent Errors and Contradictions in your precedent <hi>Reply:</hi> But inſtead of that, I find it full gorged with a Pragmatick Cenſure (to call it no worſe) of the Converſation and Deportment as well of the <hi>Gentry</hi> as <hi>Clergie,</hi> of the Writings of worthy <hi>Authors,</hi> and of the Affairs of Publick Government, an excurſion ſo much above your Capacity and Station, and ſo fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign to your Province, and the ſubject of your Diſcourſe, that (doubtleſs) all ſober men will agree, that it deſerves the ſevereſt blame and reprehenſion, rather than the honour of an <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However, I cannot but take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of two Paſſages in it, which are two other ſorts of Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents that make it diſtaſteful and nauſeous to all <hi>Catholick Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:175149:57"/>
            <p>The firſt is your looſe Queſtion to the Parſon of <hi>Bocking,</hi> Page 130. <hi>Whether if I believed in God and Chriſt, I were obliged to be a Member of any particular Church, or no?</hi> I ſhall anſwer it in ſhort; You know very well, that you may believe in, as well as worſhip the true God and our Saviour, after a wrong and falſe manner, as the various and oppoſite Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſions under Chriſtianity at large, make too much manifeſt; and then what ſatisfaction and aſſurance you can have out of the Communion of the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> (which worſhips the true God after the true manner, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his revealed and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Declarations, (not to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with his extraordinary Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations) I leave you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider.</p>
            <p>And as to the Parſon of <hi>Bock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>'s
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:175149:58"/>Golden Anſwer (as you call it) <hi>That if you were one of God's <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church, 'twas no great matter whether you were joyned to any petty Church policy here on earth, or no.</hi> He might make uſe of this Saying, to palliate a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with the ſeveral Changes in the Times, as if any or no Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline at all were very indifferent; therefore to come up cloſe to him, I do not underſtand what Church can be termed God's Church U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal, except that which from its holding and profeſſing all the Fundamentals of Doctrine and Faith contained in the Goſpel, is truly called <hi>Catholick,</hi> which hath had power in all Ages to eſtabliſh its own Diſcipline, Rites and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, to all which its Member are obliged to Conform for the ſake of Unity and Communion, the two grand external Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:175149:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>and Accompliſhments of the true Worſhip and Religion.</p>
            <p>The next Paſſage is <hi>pag.</hi> 139. <hi>by which</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> Reaſon) <hi>and by no other mediation, it is poſſible for a man of good underſtanding, and not clogged with falſe Principles, to be ſatisfied that the natural Dictates of God (Reaſon) carry no repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy in them to the Law and Will of God revealed in the Scripture,</hi> &amp;c. This Averment (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all your palliating Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances) muſt neceſſarily be underſtood of <hi>Reaſon</hi> corrupted; for right <hi>Reaſon</hi> being above our degenerated Capacity, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe not the Province to defend, can neither be the Subject of the Queſtion in this Clauſe, nor of any other part of your diſcourſe: Now then if lapſed Reaſon is ſo perfectly righteous, and that the Will cannot but follow the laſt
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:175149:59"/>dictate of that (as you have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared heretofore) then no man can offend or need any repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; a Principle ſo prophane, and of ſo hainous a tincture, that we never hear of it mentioned by the moſt barbarous Heathens. Nay had you but conſidered that in the ſhort <hi>Epoche</hi> of <hi>Innocence,</hi> when <hi>Adam</hi> was endued with Humane Reaſon in its higheſt and moſt perſpicacious degree; it was not ſo perfectly fixed, as to guide him in his obedience to one Command of the Deity, for his preſervation in Paradice, you muſt either out of ſhame or dread have been diſcouraged to have offered ſuch Sentiments to the World.</p>
            <p>But for an entire and final con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincement of this <hi>Apologiſt,</hi> let him own or diſallow the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Scriptures, it cannot
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:175149:59"/>(on the one hand) be denied, but that the imbecility of our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding (according to the tenor of Holy Writ) is a juſt and genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine puniſhment for our firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents Ambition to obtain a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge againſt the Command of the Deity, and above the ſtate of a Creature; and on the other, every days experience evinces (without revelation) that Fancy and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour uſurp a very great ſhare in the Regiment here below, of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Tranſactions, which Reaſon claims to be its proper Sphere of activity and natural dominion.</p>
            <p>To this it may be added for the confirming of this Argument, that Infallibility is the peculiar as well as the inſeparable Attribute of an Omniſcient Being, which admits of no higher Underſtanding to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe or confute it; And ſince this cannot be truly affirmed of any
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:175149:60"/>being that is created, the Creature of it ſelf muſt (conſequently) labor under a general ſubjection to er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour from its general imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the higheſt inſtance to prove this, is the fall of thoſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels who revolted from the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip as well as from their Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to the Deity.</p>
            <p>Therefore I leave the <hi>Reader</hi> to judge, whether this <hi>Apologiſts</hi> fantaſtick Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and Cenſure which he puts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on others, is not due to himſelf, <hi>That he ought to be reckoned among the number of the delirious,</hi> for attempting to defend the Infallibility of Humane Reaſon, without the leaſt evidence to ſupport it either Humane or Divine. After all this advertiſement, if he ſhall be given to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribling (as he hath vaunted to <hi>Plain-dealing</hi>) I hope the higheſt <hi>Bigots</hi> to <hi>Novelty</hi> (from a luxuriancy of Wit) will for the future be convinced, that ſuch wretched diſcourſes as theſe can only deſerve a publick Reprimand.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
